<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-12T14:40:03-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Lewis Connolly</title><subtitle>This is the website of Lewis Connolly. I write about meaning, philosophy, spirituality, history, and psychology. I’m particularly interested in belief, because people do not act on truths; it’s their beliefs that move them.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Geometrics of Taste</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/01/12/the-geometrics-of-taste/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Geometrics of Taste" /><published>2025-01-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-01-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/01/12/the-geometrics-of-taste</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/01/12/the-geometrics-of-taste/"><![CDATA[<div class="post">
    <audio class="audio-player" controls="">
        <source src="/assets/audio/Deco.mp3" type="audio/mpeg" />
    </audio>
    <!-- Blog content here -->
</div>

<p><img src="/assets/images/deco.png" alt="Taste" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 600px; height: auto;" /></p>

<p>           In this essay, I’ll explore design—interior design, website design, and its ties to marketing—examining how taste shapes the spaces we create, their purpose, and how they reflect our individuality and aspirations.</p>

<p>           I’m a fan of Art Deco, which has its origins at the 1925 Paris Exhibition, but I think of it as primarily a 1920s and 30s American style, finding expression in architecture, product design, and interior design. Perhaps the most well-known example in the 21st Century is ‘The Great Gatsby’ (2013). The movie itself was a bit blah, but it is visually stunning. Art Deco is luxurious, glamorous, and feels very optimistic about the future and human progress. It’s an artistic movement that contrasts sharply with the pervasive pessimism and cynicism that you find among many young Americans today, exemplified by antinatalism, climate despair, a skepticism of technology and progress, and a preoccupation with identitarianism. All very tiresome.</p>

<p>           The term ‘Art Deco’ was popularized by the English historian, Bevis Hillier, used in the first academic book on the subject, ‘Art Deco of the 20s and 30s’ (1968). He sees Art Deco as having a playful relationship to previous artistic movements: cubism, Art Nouveau, high fashion, the aerodynamic shapes of planes and automobiles with their chrome finishes. It embraced elements of Neoclassicism, with its sense of order and grandeur, and even Egyptology, sparked by the opening of Tutankhamun’s tomb in 1922. This was all brought to a screeching halt by the Great Depression of the 1930s. Unlike the modernism which followed, which I find can be a bit too sparse, functional, and grey, I like the exuberance, color and playfulness of Art Deco. I like that it’s willing to put a striking totemic ornamental flourish right at the center of a space just because it looks cool.</p>

<p>           Spaces serve different functions. Different spaces draw different types of experiences out of us. I like the Goethe quote, “Music is liquid architecture; Architecture is frozen music.” It’s as if spaces play us. When we think of interior design, we’re thinking about curating spaces, trying to realize a particular vision in them. Ultimately, though, it’s about how these spaces—our homes—make us feel. And so, although the means or the medium is the exterior or objective space in question, the ends are really our own interior space. You might find certain styles impressive, masterful, or intriguing, and they can be appreciated as such, but our own curated space needs to be our own, expressions of ourselves, our personality. It needs to play the notes that resonate with our interior selves.</p>

<div style="margin-top: 30px;"></div>
<p><img src="/assets/images/asterism1.png" alt="Asterism" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 85px; height: auto;" /></p>
<div style="margin-bottom: 30px;"></div>

<p>           In the last month, I’ve been doing a website re-design from the ground up. For the last ten years I’ve been diligently paying my $20 a month Squarespace subscription (which is an easy-to-use drag-and-drop website making tool). I was wondering if there was another way to go. Note that I have no web developer or coding experience, but I thought that with a few prompts on ChatGPT it might be possible now to generate a website that I could host somewhere for free. It was more difficult than I would have guessed. But after learning about github.com and discovering Jekyll, a static site generator, I eventually pieced everything together through trial and error. Unless you want to learn this stuff and have some time on your hands, I wouldn’t follow my example. After all, at the rate things are going technologically speaking, give it 6 months to a year, and I’m sure this will all be a lot easier.</p>

<p>           So, I’ve been thinking about design. In the world of website design there is a lot of free stuff out there now—complete templates included. But I took the “make things unnecessarily difficult for myself” approach and started from scratch. This has resulted in the minimalistic, monochromatic, I think stylish website that lies before you – very much an evolving work in progress.</p>

<p>           It’s all about focus. I recently set up my support page —so that you can toss me a few bucks if you’re so inclined. <a href="https://buymeacoffee.com/lewisconnolly" target="_blank">My virtual tip jar.</a> While working on this, I checked out some other websites from creators and writers who have also set up a support page, and the pattern was clear: success comes from having a specific website focus. Here’s an interesting case study: <a href="https://tracesoftexas.com/" target="_blank">tracesoftexas.com</a> the website URL tells you almost everything you need to know. This is a website about Texas. Let me tell you about it. It’s a pretty amateurish website. It is not that visually appealing, it doesn’t take much clicking around to find broken links, and there’s not even a lot on the website. It’s really just a landing page that points you in two directions: towards a website where the creator is selling some Texas-themed photographs, and towards a low-traffic forum where various Texas-related topics are discussed—history, restaurants, cities, etc. It’s not much to look at, and yet this is, monetarily speaking, a successful website.</p>

<p>           So why might that be? Perhaps people like supporting the creator, maybe they like his photographs, or his writings. But as weird as it sounds, I think that’s only a part of what’s going on here. This is probably an unfair characterization, but I think a lot of the support has more to do with the supporters than the output of the creator. How would you even come upon such a website? Probably because you feel like you’re the sort of person who has an affinity for Texas, a love of Texas culture, Texas history, Texas beauty, and by way of a bit of Googling you’ve found yourself on that website. It goes to the core of how you think of yourself. You’re probably from there, or you live there. And if you take the extra step of throwing this website a buck, you are reinforcing your own self-identity. Now you’re not just someone who loves Texas; you love it so much that you’re willing to throw a buck at a website all about this passion of yours. You’re willing to put your money where your mouth is. Academics call this “identity purchasing.”</p>

<p>           What’s even weirder is, even if you never actually get around to looking at this guy’s photographs or reading any of his articles, in giving a contribution, your own sense of identity will have been reinforced anyway. There’s something very powerful at play here. I also think American tipping culture is playing into all this too. The act of handing over the buck is normalized here in a way that it’s just not where I’m from. I don’t think I really understand American money culture. They’re touchier in some ways, but then again, not at all in other ways. As a Brit, doing the whole, “If this content has been valuable to you, your support is appreciated” grift, does not come to me naturally – but I’ll get there. I included the link didn’t I?</p>

<p style="margin: 0; line-height: 1.7; padding: 0;">
    &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; When it comes to the whole 
    <a href="https://tracesoftexas.com/" target="_blank" style="text-decoration: none;">tracesoftexas.com</a> dynamic I've been discussing, my own website completely misses the mark. Perhaps I should say, my focus is not having a focus. In the last month I’ve written articles on the American cattle industry
    <a href="https://lewisconnolly.com/2024/12/18/Bovine-Chronicles-Untold/" target="_blank" style="text-decoration: none; border: none; display: inline-block; line-height: 0; vertical-align: baseline;">
        <img src="/assets/images/footnote/no1.png" alt="Footnote 1" style="width: 15px; height: 15px; margin: 0; padding: 0; position: relative; top: -7px; vertical-align: middle; display: inline;" />
    </a>, a reflection on a piece of horror literature
    <a href="https://lewisconnolly.com/2025/01/02/in-wonderlands-shadow/" target="_blank" style="text-decoration: none; border: none; display: inline-block; line-height: 0; vertical-align: baseline;">
        <img src="/assets/images/footnote/no2.png" alt="Footnote 2" style="width: 15px; height: 15px; margin: 0; padding: 0; position: relative; top: -7px; vertical-align: middle; display: inline;" />
    </a>, and laid out an idea for a new computer game.
    <a href="https://lewisconnolly.com/2024/12/11/the-10,000-person-puzzle/" target="_blank" style="text-decoration: none; border: none; display: inline-block; line-height: 0; vertical-align: baseline;">
        <img src="/assets/images/footnote/no3.png" alt="Footnote 3" style="width: 15px; height: 15px; margin: 0; padding: 0; position: relative; top: -7px; vertical-align: middle; display: inline;" />
    </a> The smart thing to do would be to create a new website, perhaps: DreadfulTales.com, CowsAndCountry.com, or PlayConcepts.com, throw a few articles on there every few weeks and cash-in on some of those sweet identity purchasing bucks. I’ve considered it. It would be far more marketable, but it’s definitely not me. For me, writing is not an obligation but a dance with inspiration—free, heartfelt, and unbound by any constraints.
</p>

<div style="margin-top: 30px;"></div>
<p><img src="/assets/images/asterism2.png" alt="Asterism" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 85px; height: auto;" /></p>
<div style="margin-bottom: 40px;"></div>

<p>           I think of my website as a kind of commonplace book—a space to gather my thoughts, explore ideas as they come to me, and give form to my creative output. Visiting a “personal” website like this, I think should be like dropping by for <del>a coffee</del> a beer. In this space you can get a sense of my interior thought world. I wonder if in the future it won’t feel a lot more like that, like dropping by. Digital space will feel more like the material world; you will enter my rooms, and see the spaces that I have curated. The tasteful back-lit olive tree in the corner. The sound of birds coming in through the Greco-Roman colonnades. The clink of a glass as its put down on a black marble bar gilded with geometric patterns. We will run our fingers along the contours of such aesthetic particulars. Our tastes will inform the spaces we create, and the spaces that we occupy.</p>

<p>           Website design, in my view, has a lot in common with interior design. ‘Websites’ will no longer be the appropriate term, but these domains will become one and the same. In this future, truth, reason, and compute will all be cheap, essentially worthless, being infinitely available to everyone all the time. So, in such a reality, you obviously would not enter someone else’s domain in order to learn a fact. Rather, what is of value would be some interplay between relationships and aesthetics.</p>

<p>           I made a related point in a previous article regarding taste; <a href="https://lewisconnolly.com/2024/12/27/A-Taste-of-Deeper-Things/" target="_blank" style="display: inline; text-decoration: none; border: none;"><img src="/assets/images/footnote/no4.png" alt="Footnote 4" style="width: 15px; height: 15px; vertical-align: text-bottom; margin-left: -3px; margin-right: -1px; position: relative; top: 7px; display: inline; border: none;" /></a> an artificial intelligence in the future may be able to perform any task you want, do any job, but it will not be able to tell you what spaces you like to inhabit, that speak to your soul. These will be our museums of aesthetic delight. These pleasure gardens.</p>

<p>           In such a world, the value of these domains will lie in their ability to surprise, to captivate, to resonate. They will not exist to answer questions but to spark a childlike wonder of things—to draw you into a conversation with the space itself, with its creator, and with your own sensibilities. Like stepping into a friend’s gallery, you’ll find yourself lingering over the unexpected: the interplay of shadows, sounds held in a moment, some curious juxtaposition of things. These spaces will be less about utility and more about communion—a meeting place for feelings, and experiences that lie beyond any algorithm.</p>

<p>           With this analogy that I’ve painted, however, I have cast you, the reader, into this virtual domain as a distinct being. I imagine such distinctions as dissolvable: it’s one thing to experience my aesthetic appreciations as you, and another to experience it as me. There’s the experience, and then there is the experiencer. The world is showing up differently to me now, in my late 30s, than it did when I was a child. Our inexplicable states of being are constantly shaping the way we interface with reality. Yesterday, I wrote nothing; I felt no compulsion to do so—nothing was fizzing. Today, though, the words are flowing nicely. Being able to manipulate such underlying impulses would be glorious. I recall catching glimpses of alternative tracks of perception, I would love to fall in, like Proustian moments of eternal recurrence. It brings to mind psychonauts who use psychoactive substances to explore alternative states of consciousness. We will be “cybernauts,” playing our way across rooms, filled with levels of granular aesthetic attributes currently beyond our imagining.</p>

<div style="margin-top: 30px;"></div>
<p><img src="/assets/images/asterism1.png" alt="Asterism" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 85px; height: auto;" /></p>
<div style="margin-bottom: 40px;"></div>

<p>           Given this vision of multi-sensory digital experience, we can begin bringing elements of this into our website design now. When we’re creating or curating, I don’t see much difference between the two; there’s a distinction to be made between recognizing that something looks good and is done well, and recognizing when something reflects our own unique aesthetic preferences. While there are many stylish templates available out there, no generic template is going to fully reflect our particulars, the essence of our soul. We’re going to need to go deep. Obviously, when it comes to website design, elements like spacing, layout, typography, images, and color are minor details in the grand scheme of things. Is anyone’s soul really going to be captured in a website? I’m not so sure. But it’s a means to an end. In going through this process, you’re, in effect, coding your aesthetic DNA into the universe—you’re giving tomorrow’s supercomputers something to work with. You are, in essence, programming your soul into the future.</p>

<p>           Most of the images on my website are created using ChatGPT. I go through a prompting and curating process, trying to find what works. I considered changing my website logo. I’ve been experimenting with it. The logo is currently the letter ‘C’ - the first letter in my surname – Connolly. I used a monochromatic color palette, it has a flowing, wave-like curve to it, and I aimed to achieve a balance between minimalism and visual intrigue. On the home page the logo is static, on other pages when you hover over it, it changes from a darker color to an off white, and it slightly enlarges. Wherever the logo appears throughout the website it acts as a link to bring you back to the home page.</p>

<p>           Given my affinity for art deco, I decided to iteratively refine my logo to reflect that. See images below. My prompts included: art deco, images which invoked technology, futurism, neoclassical design; I like light blue, I think it invokes a kind of electric type feel. What you see below is a selection of what most appealed to me. The three in the far-right column are probably my favorites. Ultimately, however, I don’t think any of them are as good as my current logo. And so, I’m sticking, for now.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/logos.png" alt="Taste" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 800px; height: auto;" /></p>

<p>           I went through a similar process for selecting the fleurons on my website. Fleurons are those decorative typographical elements you find between some paragraphs. I chose them to create a more intentional transition from one paragraph—or one idea—to the next. I think the ones I chose hit the sweet spot; they make the reader’s experience better, serving a utilitarian purpose, marking that more intentional transition, and I like the way they look, sitting at the intersection between a forward-looking art deco past, and tomorrow’s cyber future. In the end, design is not just about aesthetics but about creating spaces — “real” or digital — that resonate with who we are.</p>]]></content><author><name>Lewis Connolly</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">In Wonderland’s Shadow</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/01/02/in-wonderlands-shadow/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In Wonderland’s Shadow" /><published>2025-01-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-01-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/01/02/in-wonderlands-shadow</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/01/02/in-wonderlands-shadow/"><![CDATA[<div class="post">
    <audio class="audio-player" controls>
        <source src="/assets/audio/Alice.mp3" type="audio/mpeg">
    </audio>
    <!-- Blog content here -->
</div>

<img src="{{ '/assets/images/Alicepic.png' | relative_url }}" alt="Taste" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 600px; height: auto;">

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This article discusses topics related to sexual abuse. My focus will be a discussion on ‘Alice’s Last Adventure’, a short-story from the 'weird fiction' writer Thomas Ligotti. I don’t particularly like trigger warnings. To me, if a shocking subject appears on the page, the writer should have already earned the right to address it. Good writing, after all, should have built the literary space necessary to engage with the topic at hand. It’s not dissimilar to when you unveil a shocking truth to a friend in a deep conversation; you’re willing to go there, because mutual trust has already been established. I suppose the purpose of such a warning is to reduce unintentional harm. I suspect, however, that it probably acts as more of a literary hook; the voyeur leans in, curious as to what will be said.

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In my previous article, [‘A Taste of Deeper Things’](https://lewisconnolly.com/2024/12/27/A-Taste-of-Deeper-Things/) I spoke on taste in relation to four pieces of art I “like”. Given that these are all substantive pieces that I endeavor to cover in a few paragraphs, I couldn’t possibly have done them or my own taste justice. In makes me wonder how granular critique should be? How close should one stand? A paragraph away, a sentence, should I pontificate at length on the feelings evoked from a single word?

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; I heard recently that if several people hum the same familiar tune, their brain scans would reveal a distinct, individualized thumbprint of neural activity. The reason for this might be rather obvious: each word, each sound, causes within us a unique set of associations, unique firing of brain activity. Take a piece of instrumental music. If we were to self-examine our own emotional response, we could probably identify melodic shifts from one chord to another that touch us most intensely. With the use of neural imaging technology, perhaps entire pieces of music could be composed that speak to our particular neurological makeup.

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Why merely stand close, when we can enter minds? But maybe this wouldn’t work; it summons thoughts of the 19th Century English  painter, William Turner, who’s later work took on such an expressionistic style that in close proximity all one can discern is a confused blur of color, but far enough back, and you’re looking upon his masterful landscapes. John Ruskin described them as being able to "stirringly and truthfully measure the moods of Nature". Could it be said that stepping back weakens our appreciation? Obviously not. I think also of the 20th Century American abstract painter Mark Rothko. In reference to his most famous works, his Color Field paintings, he recommended (I imagine whimsically) that his viewers position themselves eighteen inches from the canvas. He wanted his work to envelope you; this is why he made them so big, in order to create intimacy. 

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Of course, in a way the prose writer does enter the mind. I can feel so much dumber when I’m not reading good prose. Having thoughts of one’s own, and reading the thoughts of others, can feel very similar. Is reading not like going on a thinking simulation, where your interior voice becomes the writer’s voice, closer even than breath? I mentioned ‘voyeurism’ above, and I think there is something voyeuristic about the reader/writer relationship. My most intimately present reality is the thoughts that I’m having, and when I write, the page becomes an extension of my thought world. The reader penetrates my mind. I know they’re there in the abstract, but I don’t know who’s there, I don’t know who is closer than breath. Perhaps you could even say, in this moment, it doesn’t seem like there is any distinction at all; there is no reader/writer boundary, there is just the thought held here in mind.

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Now to turn to ‘Alice’s Last Adventure’ by Thomas Ligotti. Thomas Ligotti (born in 1953) is a contemporary American fiction writer, in the dark, horror, weird fiction genres, with an eye towards philosophy and psychology. The story can be found in one of his short-story collections, “Songs of a Dead Dreamer and Grimscribe” (2015) - a friend recommended it to me.  It feels very reductionist to say that you like something. Saying as much actually annoys me on an irrational level, what does ‘you like something’ even mean? Hence my current monomaniacal investigation of taste. Take a joke: you wouldn’t say you “like” a joke, well you might, but don’t. Rather, if it merits it, you laugh at the joke, or you at least give it a knowing smirk. Once the joke is out there, you can then discuss it, the mechanics of it, the form, the setup, and so forth, and you may even explain the joke to those who don’t get it. An essay on a short story feels a lot like that - an exercise in explaining the joke. Isn’t that the role everyone secretly wants?

<img src="{{ '/assets/images/asterism1.png' | relative_url }}" alt="Asterism" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 85px; height: auto;">
<div style="margin-bottom: 40px;"></div>

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Ligotti’s story draws inspiration from Lewis Carroll’s most iconic works, ‘Alice’s Adventures in Wonderland’ (1865) and ‘Through the Looking-Glass’ (1871). Lewis Carroll himself is barely discussed in the short story, but his identity goes to the very core of it. So, first, let me paint myself into the frame. My name is Lewis, and I am named after Lewis Carroll, and like the protagonist in the short story, I too have memories of my father reading ‘Through the Looking-Glass’ to me as a child. So, there’s a curious sort of paralleling at play, though, obviously, devoid of all the dark undertones I will discuss.

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Lewis Carroll was his pen name; his real name was Rev. Charles Dodgson (1832 – 1898). He was a writer, a mathematician, photographer, and a lifelong childless bachelor. He came close to being ordained a priest in the Church of England, but ended up a rather reluctant lifelong deacon. In 19th Century England the norm was for all Oxbridge ‘dons’ (fellows and tutors) to be Anglican Clergy; this requirement began to loosen in the latter half of the century. For most of his life he lectured at Christ Church, Oxford, and even in later life when fame and fortune came, he continued his lecturing in mathematics. 

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The Alice books are obviously what he is best known for. These books were inspired by his relationship with the ten-year-old girl, Alice Liddell. Dodgson was a family friend of the Liddells. Alice, while out on a rowing boat trip with Dodgson and others, asked him to tell her a story; he constructed a fantastical narrative about a girl called Alice who fell down a rabbit hole and went on many wondrous adventures. A few months later the story was written up into the manuscript, ‘Alice’s Adventures in Wonderland’. There has been much speculation over the years as to whether Dodgson had an erotic interest in children. 

<img src="{{ '/assets/images/girl.png' | relative_url }}" alt="Taste" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 600px; height: auto;">

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Although a relationship between a single male adult and a little girl in today’s world is only acceptable in the narrowest of domains, such was not the case in 19th Century England. As I said, Dodgson was a photographer. He took many portraits of artists, celebrities, and friends, but he enjoyed most of all taking photographs of Alice Liddell and her sisters. He spent a great deal of time with these girls in his rooms and going on outings. He was enlivened in the company of children. Indeed, he also had a collection of drawings and photographs of nude children, often in risqué postures. Again, although by modern standards this would be unacceptable, in Victorian England it was not controversial. So, was he infatuated? In love? Did these relationships go further than friendship? We do not know… But I will quote Will Self, who says, “It’s a problem, isn’t it? It’s a problem when someone writes a great book and they’re not a great person” (The Secret World of Lewis Carroll, BBC, 2015).

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Because of the nature of such speculation, people are of course inclined to have strong opinions one way or another. I don’t know what Thomas Ligotti personally believes; it’s not really relevant, but given his pessimistic view of humanity it’s probably fair to assume he imagines the worst. Regardless, however, I believe his short story operates on the presumptive premise that Charles Dodgson was indeed sexually abusing Alice Liddell. It is never said, but I don’t think what follows makes much sense otherwise. As well as the Alice books, I believe the story is also influenced by Vladimir Nabokov’s work, in particular ‘Pale Fire’ (1962), and ‘Lolita’ (1955). ‘Lolita’ is a first-person narrative from the perspective of the protagonist, Humbert Humbert. It is a memoir about his sexual interest in a twelve-year old girl; in other words it’s written by the abuser, and everything is filtered through his first-person perspective - a perspective which has a self-serving agenda. Everything about the girl, the abusee, as such, comes to us through this unreliable filter. 

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; You could see the Alice books in a similar light. The narrator’s voice is the voice of the abuser, who is Lewis Carroll. The titular character, the idealized girl, who is the simulacrum of Alice Liddell, is Carroll’s plaything. She sits within the fulcrum of the abuser’s fantasy world. The abusee therefore only comes to us mediated, a marionette doll, silent.

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Ligotti’s ‘Alice’s Last Adventure’ follows Alice, whose father affectionately calls her “little moon face” and reads her ‘Through the Looking-Glass’, the book from which she has been named. Writing in the first person through a journal, Alice’s narrative echoes Nabokov’s ‘Pale Fire’ and ‘Lolita’, where unreliable protagonist/narrators frame reality through their warped perspectives. Like Nabokov’s characters, Alice’s story demands attention to the unsaid, as her account is clouded by bias and distortion.

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Now an older woman, Alice became a fiction writer, shaped by her father’s influence. Her protagonist, Preston Penn, is a mischievous boy modeled on a childhood friend, who is forever frozen in childhood— in the course of her books we’re told he enters an upside-down and sinister universe, paralleling Carroll’s Wonderland. Alice’s father, a philosophy professor, revered Carroll, viewing him as a “psychic supreme” who willed Wonderland’s Alice into being and controlled her fictional realm. This reflects how he then saw his daughter: a creation of his will, existing within his world for his pleasure. Subtle hints—his “childlike” demeanor and fixation on her as “his Alice”—suggest disturbing undertones in their relationship.
She writes, “When I got older, my features became more angular, an involuntary betrayal of my father’s conception of his little Alice,”. In other words, or at least my sense of this passage is that her father is a pedophile, and that as Alice got older, he lost interest in her. Even after his death, Alice appears trapped in a state of arrested development, seeking to embody the child he adored. This psychic paralysis shaped her career, leading her to write about childish things, preserving a sense of herself as deserving of his love.

<img src="{{ '/assets/images/asterism1.png' | relative_url }}" alt="Asterism" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 85px; height: auto;">
<div style="margin-bottom: 50px;"></div>

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Alice describes a life scarred by trauma: breakdowns, failed marriages, addiction, and widowhood. While we’re not told the explicit reason for this, these struggles seem rooted in the childhood trauma. In her journal, she shifts to recent events, noting a creeping strangeness over the past year—a “lack of tidiness” in her life. This phrase connects to earlier discussions of the mirror in ‘Through the Looking-Glass’, where the world on the other side is “not as tidy.” Carroll’s Alice recognizes this; Ligotti’s Alice does not. She fails to see that she has already gone through the looking glass. She is now in that upside down and sinister realm. By her own reckoning, all this is down to the fact that she is drinking heavily again. So, she’s writing to try and make sense of all this. Unlike Nabokov’s protagonists who are trying to persuade the reader of something, it is unclear if she is even writing with a reader in mind, and as such, I’m not sure she’s trying to convince anyone of anything, apart from perhaps herself. This arguably brings us even closer into her mind, into her misshapen neurological makeup.

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; She looks up at the clock; it has stopped at eleven p.m. It transpires that she is writing on Halloween night, having returned from a local library’s Halloween party, where she had given a reading from one of her Preston Penn books. This was an annual tradition. The year prior, however, she had to cancel, because she went to a funeral. The funeral was for the unnamed childhood friend who had inspired the Preston Penn character. She says that she had not seen him since her twentieth birthday, which was soon after her father had died. 

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The funeral is being held in the town she’s from; it feels to her as if she has gone back in time. I think the idea is that this town is the realm that was willed into creation by her father, a sinister realm that is populated, like Carroll’s world is, with a cast of oddballs. Some of these characters are like-for-like, mirrored versions of Carroll’s characters. Take, for example, a man with a walrus mustache who serves ice cream to two big-bellied children. This imagery recalls Tweedledee and Tweedledum singing to Alice the story of "The Walrus and the Carpenter", in which the Walrus and the Carpenter coax young oysters along the beach, only to devour them. I picture a sinister reimagining of the Pied Piper of Hamelin luring children away with his magic pipe in order that he might “devour” them.

<img src="{{ '/assets/images/piper.png' | relative_url }}" alt="Taste" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 600px; height: auto;">

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; After the funeral home viewing, she goes to a nice hotel; there she meets a man who she has dinner with and takes back to her room. At some point in the night, she awakens. As the story progresses, it becomes increasingly difficult to interpret events through what we would typically recognize as a normative sense of reality. She wakes in the night to some odd movement, makes her way over to a mirror, which appears for a moment to show a corpse's head, until she realizes that it is her own face looking back at her. She sums up her sense from the year that is passed as “half-conscious perceptions, and the distortions of memory”, before turning her attention back to today: Halloween. 

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; After a sleepless night, she had found herself in the bathroom, washing and creaming herself, and there sitting on the toilet tank is her cat, “Chessie” - once again, a nod to Carroll’s Cheshire Cat. The cat that, probably most pertinently to all this, says, “You must be mad, or you wouldn’t have come here.” Ligotti’s Alice then talks about having seen something squiggle around in the toilet, something that startled the cat. This all has to do with, as I said before, her having gone through the looking glass. If we think of Carroll’s Alice, she is a matter-of-fact girl who is in her right mind, reacting to this very odd world into which she has been thrust. Ligotti’s Alice, on the other hand, is a woman or girl who is unable to integrate the horrors of the “real world” she is experiencing. And as such, in Jungian terms, she, without knowing, represses that material. It now resides within her unconscious mind, in the shadow world, or might I say in wonderland. 

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; So, what is really going on? What is this horror? I only have a sense of that; I think one possibility is that whereas Carrolls’ Alice, in going down the rabbit hole, escaped a mundane second-rate reality to arrive in a surreal and illogical one, Ligotti’s Alice goes down the hole to escape the surreal and illogical, to escape the world of her father’s making, a world of systematic abuse. She escapes into a world where she is a successful author, with money, who does recitals, and perhaps in this world she will even be able to please her father, not through her form, but through the content of her mind. But now her wonderland is crashing up against reality; they’re bleeding into one another. But we’re unable to step back, unable to gain any perspective. We’re enveloped here in this confusing blur. 

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; She’s now getting ready to go to that Halloween party to give her reading. She says that the children make her nervous, and that’s why she’s never adopted any. Having them was never an option, as she was infertile. Given my interpretation, I’ll allow you to imagine why that might be. The only way she was able to cope with the recital at all was a lot of pre-drinking.

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Having arrived and done the necessary pleasantries, she’s led to where she will perform. In the final section, the blur, the weird, is at peak crescendo; sexual inuendo is thick on the page. She’s led not to the children’s section where such readings ordinarily took place but down into the basement. “A small auditorium of sorts.” You can hear screaming. Is this the bedlam of children? Now on the stage, “the half-crocked lady author was about to deliver a half-cocked oration.” The lights were switched off. There’s a commotion, one of the children faints, “the poor thing hyperventilated or something like that.” It seems that some of these children were making a mistake that Alice was not, they were entirely present. “Amazing how children can put things right out of their minds and recover so quickly.” Perhaps this is the nightmare of some kiddie orgy that’s coming flooding back, or perhaps she’s still there now.

&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; But she’s writing in her room. She notices that the moon is turned the wrong way, everything is wrong. There is a sound of giggling in the hallway; she doesn’t know if it’s inside or outside her head. All the boundaries have been dissolved, is it an interior or an exterior sound? It is such a familiar laugh – “I’ve been good. I just got old, that’s all. Please stop.” But her father’s abuse didn’t stop.]]></content><author><name>Lewis Connolly</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Taste of Deeper Things</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/27/A-Taste-of-Deeper-Things/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Taste of Deeper Things" /><published>2024-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/12/27/A-Taste-of-Deeper-Things</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/27/A-Taste-of-Deeper-Things/"><![CDATA[<div class="post">
    <audio class="audio-player" controls>
        <source src="/assets/audio/taste.mp3" type="audio/mpeg">
    </audio>
    <!-- Blog content here -->
</div>

<img src="{{ '/assets/images/taste.png' | relative_url }}" alt="Taste" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 600px; height: auto;">

Lately, I can't seem to stop thinking about taste. Taste is elusive; I know what I like, but articulating why I like it is a far greater challenge. The reasons behind our preferences often defy clarity, as though the very idea of 'reason' cannot capture the instinctive pull of our preferences. It remains buried in the unconscious mind—a realm of unspoken memories and intangible connections—where art strikes at chords within the self.

To speak of such things—of taste—is, I think, necessary, personal, and a most human endeavor. For reasons I will explain, I’m going to discuss four pieces of art: a film, a series, a book, and an album, four pieces that I like and that have stayed with me. The four are: Darren Aronofsky’s ‘The Fountain’ (2006), ‘Six Feet Under’ (2001 – 2005), ‘The Rings of Saturn’ (English publication 1998) by W. G. Sebald, and Loudon Wainwright III’s second album titled ‘Album II’ (1971), focusing on the sixth track ‘Saw Your Name in the Paper’. So, on the surface these four pieces are obviously very different. The film is a trippy science fiction romance which jumps around in time. The series is a drama set in a funeral home in Los Angeles. The book is a first-person narrative about a man going for a walk along the Suffolk coastline in England. And the album is a sparse collection of folk songs, just vocals and a guitar.

Now, I will be going into each of these in more detail and attempting to express why I think each of them resonates, but as I have already intimated, I expect I'll fall short of this. I do believe, however, that something at play has to do with when one is laid out bare, when one strips away pretense, and when one is willing to meet, and be met by, the other. These works extend an invitation to step into their shared emotional space. I’m not that fond of small talk—it can be exhausting and unfulfilling – but in a real conversation there is a sense of mutual presence, where the weight of the moment can be tangibly felt. When one is honest, vulnerable, and real, there is a sense of being on the brink of something essential. These four pieces invite us into this kind of conversation.

In ‘The Fountain’ (2006), starring Hugh Jackman and Rachel Weisz, the protagonist sets out to discover the tree of life, the tree from the garden of Eden. The narrative draws on the motifs of a knight on a heraldic grail quest. He is on his hero’s journey to discover immortality, healing, and wholeness. Queen Isabella in the 16th Century is on the brink of losing her kingdom to the inquisition; she sends out her conquistador to central America on this most sacred mission. The narrative is non-linear; we jump through three interwoven timelines, each separated by 500 years. The protagonist is now in the 26th Century, having taken on the persona of a cosmic Taoist monk who is operating on a different plain of reality, but no less in pursuit of the tree. “Take a walk with me” a voice interrupts him. He turns his head - he is now in the 21st Century, he’s a scientist. “I have too much work” he protests to his wife in frustration; she vanishes. His wife is dying, she is terminally ill, and he, the scientist, cannot help but labor after a cure. She has resigned herself to her fate, but he cannot stop. The man in all three epochs is the same man, locked into a constant archetypal pursuit after truth, purpose, eternal life, love, everything. It’s an endless cycle, like a Nietzschean loop of eternal recurrence.

The appreciation of something, I think, requires having an eye toward homage. This echoes the sentiment that teaching is the ultimate test of understanding. In the case of art, we’re seeking not just to understand how the note affects us as the recipient, but also the how, the why, and the where. Where is this note positioned within the composition in order to invoke the effect it has upon us?

‘The Fountain’ speaks in a biblical vocabulary, the language of ultimate meaning. This is certainly a large part of why the movie appeals to me: it deals with large, philosophical, existential, psychological, and spiritual questions. These are the waters in which I like to play. When he is in the darkness battling his way through the Mayan savages, he is in the underworld, the shadow world, he is descending in order to uncover the gold, the boon that lies beyond the dragon or the flaming sword, in order that he can carry it back. All very Jungian. 

<img src="{{ '/assets/images/asterism1.png' | relative_url }}" alt="Asterism" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 85px; height: auto;">
<div style="margin-bottom: 30px;"></div>

‘Six Feet Under’ (2001 – 2005): apart from the aforementioned essential conversations that it demands, it’s also philosophical and introspective in nature. This is something reflected in all four pieces; there is a tone which speaks to my taste. I’m not making the claim, however (far from it), that these four pieces are all operating on the same frequency. They are not. The high- verses low-brow distinction can be helpful in terms of classification, far less so in terms of determining quality. Elitist art can be crap, and popular art good. I would put ‘Six Feet Under’ in the latter category, good popular art. Among these four pieces, 'Six Feet Under' has the highest viewership or listenership.

Death obviously plays a large part. The dead convene with the living, although it’s always the dead as conceived of from the living’s perspective. There is no metaphysical magic here, no voices from beyond the grave. Just the hopes and fantasies of saddened minds confronting the reality of things. The cast inhabits the funeral home, a place where “normal” domestic life butts up against the visceral reality of death. Death, which is painful, at times horrific, at times joyful, and for the affected always creates voids where memories linger. The show induces a dull ache within the sternum. My roommate at university in 2009, the year I discovered and binge-watched all five seasons, reported that I was affected. He said it caused in me a pronounced depression. I think this reflects reality.

It was devastating and brilliant. I have no doubt that it affects my outlook to this day. I think of all the thinkers, from Socrates all the way down throughout history, who have seen confronting the reality of our mortality as the path towards wisdom. And I think that’s what this show is – one long reflection on death. There’s perhaps no moment as poignant as the final scene; I don’t think it’s been bested in TV history. With Sia’s ‘Breathe Me’ playing, Claire Fisher drives across the country; as she does it cuts to each beloved character one by one to watch their death, up until her own, ever begging the question, what makes for a life well lived? Where is meaning to be located?

<div id="rings-of-saturn"></div>

‘The Rings of Saturn’ is by W. G. Sebald, a German immigrant who lived in England; he taught creative writing in the city of Norwich. His book was written in German and translated into English in 1998. It’s one of my favorite books. He died in a car crash in 2001.

So, on the surface this book appears to be a travel log about a man on a walking tour of Suffolk, mainly along her coastline, and this was not far from where I was living when I discovered and read the book for the first time in 2017. As a result, I visited and walked some of the locations discussed in the book. 

The book is about digressions. We’re walking down a trail, we’re reminded of something, and that sends our minds down a rabbit hole of reflections and associations. A little Proustian – a little in memory of things past. In this way, the impressions become the focus, more than the places. He reflects on writers; he recalls a lecturer he knew who had made Charles Ramuz, a 20th Century Swiss writer, his life’s focus; he wrote about European silkworm cultivation; he reflects on the writings of the 17th Century English polymath Sir Thomas Browne, amongst much else. In these recollections and connections, the writer makes it impossible to distinguish fact from fiction. Is the narrator him? Is he talking about a lecturer he really knew, who had really made Ramuz his life’s focus? We don’t know. This uneasiness, this not knowing being invoked in us, is part of the overall effect here.

There is a lot about memory, and a lot about erosion, or atomization, the loss of context and meaning. For instance, he focuses on the buildings that are falling into the ocean along Suffolk’s coastline - there’s a whole world of meaning being literally swept away. Melancholia is both a tone invoked by the writer, and a theme explored. In invoking the works of Browne he says, “all knowledge is enveloped in darkness. What we perceive are no more than isolated lights in the abyss of ignorance, in the shadow-filled edifice of the world” (Sebald, pg. 19). 

There’s easily a PhD or two that could be written here, so I’ll jump to the conclusion. The sub-sub-text behind the writing is the Nazis and the Holocaust. Sebald’s father was a WWII German soldier. Sebald was born in May 1944, and the Nazis surrendered a year later. So, Sebald grew up in post-WWII Germany, in a country desperately trying to forget what it had done. 

This book then is about the impossibility of discussing such things – if I were take an historical fact - I could say: over six million Jews died in the Holocaust from 1941 to 1945. How can we make sense of such a statement? The point is we can’t. A historical fact as read in a textbook really gets us no closer to the reality of things. It’s all slipping away, it’s all a ghostly apparition. There was much pain – but nothing can be said of that now. 

It was on an unusually grey and overcast day in July of last year when I was travelling into Charlotte, North Carolina, on my way to the Novant Presbyterian Hospital. I was listening to the song by Wainwright III, ‘Saw your name in the paper’. It’s a rather somber reflection on fame and the trajectory that life can take. The singer was only twenty-four at the time of release. He’s singing about a girl he knew, “Maybe you'll get famous, Maybe you'll get rich”. It has a kind of detached quality to it, as if the only way we can talk about real things is to talk in this more matter-of-fact fashion, to leave our stronger emotions at the door. But they’re very obviously there, unrequited and brewing. 

He’s channeling the sage: “Take all the people give, The people all are dying, And somehow you help them live, The people will destroy you, That love will turn to hate.” He’s talking about inevitabilities, like structures, or archetypal patterns at play within the universe. You will be lifted up, you will be exalted, you will represent something far greater than yourself, and as such, it can be turned. It’s not in your control, it’s all the projections of others, smoke and mirrors. I’ve always felt there was a kind of inevitability to everything, some intricate pattern unfolding exactly as you’d expect, if you could only see the whole thing. 

My daughter was born in the second week of July. One of the least straightforward pregnancies you could imagine, but here I am, writing, over a year and a half later, and everything is more than fine. I’m not sure if it’s the tone, the themes, or the artistry of Wainwright that makes it resonate with me so strongly, but it does. It feels like someone pouring a glass of whisky and sitting down with you for a deep conversation.

<img src="{{ '/assets/images/asterism1.png' | relative_url }}" alt="Asterism" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 85px; height: auto;">
<div style="margin-bottom: 30px;"></div>

Okay, so as I started with, the point of this was to try and express something of my taste. What makes these four pieces so impactful and meaningful to me? Hopefully something of that has been articulated. Something about sitting in discomfort, and finding meaning in the midst of it. These pieces are pushing us to grapple with the complexity of things. 

I’ve been thinking about taste since I posted my article [Sunk Cost, the Meaning Crisis, & Taste](https://lewisconnolly.com/2024/11/15/sunk-cost-the-meaning-crisis-and-taste/) two months ago. My conclusion there was that writing about taste is a valuable endeavor before the arrival of AGI. As has become increasingly clear, in the coming years technology is poised to upend every paradigm. On the ARC-AGI tests, o3, OpenAI's latest model has demonstrated significantly outscoring all other models. These developments suggest that AGI may arrive sooner than anticipated, accelerating the need for preparedness. Reflecting this sentiment, Benjamin Todd ([80,000 Hours podcast](https://80000hours.org)), did a post-thread on [X on 12/22/24](https://twitter.com/ben_j_todd). It was on what we should be doing personally to prepare for AGI. Here is my paraphrased version of his list: 1. Seek out people that understand what’s going on; 2. Save money, things could get volatile; 3. Invest in things likely to do well in the runup to AGI; 4. Get citizenship in a country that will have a lot of AI wealth, i.e. the USA; 5. Might want an escape plan in place in case the nukes start dropping; 6. Prioritize things you want to be in place before AGI; 7. Don’t do anything crazy in case AGI ends up still being over a decade away. Reflecting on taste doesn’t make his list, but I think it should.

Taste is something which can never be wrong. I could convene a multidisciplinary panel of experts, or I could simply wait a few years and ask a superintelligent AI, but the response would be the same. There is much in coming years that will be upended, many livelihoods made defunct, but can taste be made wrong? Not really. 

I think we’re poised to become curators of taste. It strikes me that the future is not that dissimilar to those psychonauts of decades past – using psychedelics in the pursuit of altered states of consciousness - but these, or we, will be tomorrow’s “cybernauts” traversing phantasmagoric landscapes, traversing worlds of taste.]]></content><author><name>Lewis Connolly</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bovine Chronicles Untold</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/18/Bovine-Chronicles-Untold/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bovine Chronicles Untold" /><published>2024-12-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/12/18/Bovine-Chronicles-Untold</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/18/Bovine-Chronicles-Untold/"><![CDATA[<img src="{{ '/assets/images/cow.png' | relative_url }}" alt="Cow" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 600px; height: auto;">

A few weeks back, I re-watched ‘Temple Grandin’ (2010), a great movie about its namesake, an autistic woman, who despite the odds, entered the male-dominated American cattle industry of the 1970s and revolutionized it. Her autism allowed her to perceive feedlots—where animals are fattened for slaughter— in ways, according to her own reckoning, more akin to the cattle. As such she was able to redesign these livestock handling systems in such a way as to minimize fear and resistance.

I like the movie for its portrayal of raw ingenuity; she is able to address a problem that was previously not even recognized as one. She was able to see things afresh and make them better. It is of course satisfying when we are able to make small things better, but this was on a grand scale, an impact felt throughout the national cattle industry. It almost has that ‘A Beautiful Mind’ (2001) or ‘Limitless’ (2011) feel to it, the equations pouring down about the protagonist, an invisible world unlocked by genius.

My curiosity was piqued, so I began exploring the cattle industry. I started with a few of Temple Grandin’s lectures that are available on YouTube. Her talks, as you might expect, focus on her experience navigating the world as an autistic person and upon her work in the cattle industry. She describes herself as a strong visual thinker, which she connects to her ability to empathize with animals and understand their behavior on a fundamental level.

Grandin’s visual thinking gave her the ability to "walk through" and experience these feedlots like cattle. She got down on her hands and knees and crawled through them, seeing, hearing, and experiencing the feedlot’s narrow chutes from their perspective. This led to practical solutions that improved animal welfare, and most notably it led to her new designs, designs that are now widely utilized throughout the cattle industry.

In regard to her autism, she talks about the importance of early intervention, of identifying different cognitive styles, like visual thinking, and addressing them appropriately within an educational setting. Her example is inspiring, demonstrating as it does that by embracing one’s own unique cognitive style, it becomes possible to make distinctive, meaningful contributions. I too am a strong visual thinker, but over the years I’ve poured a great deal of effort into developing my writing skills, stretching that muscle. So that now, despite my dyslexia, I suspect that, thanks to being excessively educated, I’ve ended up in some of those rarified higher percentiles when it comes to my written communication abilities.  

Also, I suspect that, like Grandin, I’m susceptible to going on hyper-focus rampages. When I do so, I barely think about anything else until I feel I’ve sufficiently exhausted the topic at hand. No doubt some undiagnosed ADHD on my part. But anyway, when it came to the cattle industry, I certainly did not feel that I had exhausted the topic. I then stumbled upon the BQA (Beef Quality Assurance) website, where I discovered a range of free online courses about best practices in the cattle industry. So of course, I signed up for the Feedyard BQA certificate.  

This course is designed for feedyard workers, managers, and cattle producers (of which I am obviously none) to teach them about best practice when it comes to the health, safety, and welfare of cattle. Upon completion one will have demonstrated a commitment to cattle welfare and product quality. And I can now report that I am officially certified.

<img src="{{ '/assets/images/certificate.png' | relative_url }}" alt="Certificate" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 600px; height: auto;">

Now, if you’ll indulge me, I’d like to share some cattle-related factoids…

First, let’s cover bovine terminology: Bovine or cattle is the generic term for the species. A female bovine that has not yet given birth is called a heifer. Once she has given birth, she is called a cow. A male bovine is called a bull, and if he has been castrated, he is called a steer. The term “cow” is often used to refer to cattle in general, but this is technically improper usage. Note these linguistic particulars were not covered in the course.

Metal in feedlots is a big problem. It can come from many different places. But a common source is from the grain itself; when the grain is harvested, metal debris like old fence wire, nails, and shards of old machinery get incorporated into the grain. This can be combatted with the use of magnets; you might have magnets in mills, along conveyor belts, and on feed discharge points. Magnets are even put inside cattle, inserted into their first stomach (remember cattle have four, or four distinct compartments at least), there it becomes both sentinel and scavenger. The magnet will stay there for the cow’s life, and if they manage to consume only a modest diet of metal, this solution is sufficient - it will hold it all in place. But if the metal manages to puncture some internal tissues, then this will likely lead to what is called “hardware disease”, resulting in abscesses forming, severe pain, and if no treatment is possible, death. 

The course covered some interesting details about cow behavior. Despite their size, these animals aren’t prone to flashy, emotional outbursts or histrionics. Instead, cows respond predictably to their environment, guided by body positioning. With one eye on each side of their head, their binocular vision is limited, and there’s a blind spot directly behind them. Handlers learn to work within a cow’s “flight zone”—the invisible boundary that, when crossed, prompts the animal to move away instinctively. In this way handlers can guide cows in a calmer and more controlled way without having to resort to force, be that shouting or using an electric prod.

When it is determined that the best course of action is to euthanize a cow, there are several factors to consider. Euthanization may be done with a firearm, captive bolt, or an injectable euthanasia drug. For reference a captive bolt is a device which fires a metal bolt at high speed into the skull of the animal, the bolt does not detach from the gun hence the word “captive”. In ‘No Country for Old Men’ (2007), the sadistic villain Anton Chigurh uses a captive bolt as his weapon of choice. The course recommends considering the aesthetics of the situation when it comes to the euthanization of a cow. For example even though a penetrating captive bolt is an effective tool for the job, it may cause significant involuntary movement of the animal, which may be misinterpreted as a voluntary pain response; as such a firearm or euthanasia drug may be preferable. On the other hand, when it comes to the disposal of carcasses (the regulations of which are state specific, but often euthanasia by way of drugs is more heavily regulated), in order to prevent the toxins in the animal running off into ground water or being scavenged, this often leaves you with the captive bolt, or the firearm as the preferable option. One would want to use at least a .38 caliber pistol; the gun is to be held perpendicular to the skull to avoid ricochets.

What else is worth telling you? The reason handlers deal with cattle first thing in the morning is due to the temperature-humidity index, for example in the Texas panhandle, where there is a high concentration of feedlots, on an average day in the summer months the temperature and humidity in the afternoons can cross into the danger zone, as such cattle handlers prioritize working with the animals during the cooler early hours, in order to reduce the risk of heat stress.

Vaccinations should be administered into the area behind the shoulder, certainly not into high priced cut areas, as lesions in the meat reduce customer satisfaction. It is also necessary to wait until after the withdrawal period after a vaccine has been administered before a cow can be slaughtered or “harvested”, in order to ensure the safety of the meat for human consumption.

Okay, time for dinner. A marbled New York strip, medium-rare with a nice char, paired with a Cabernet Sauvignon— nothing beats it.]]></content><author><name>Lewis Connolly</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Post-Scarcity Vineyard</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/12/The-Post-Scarcity-Vineyard/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Post-Scarcity Vineyard" /><published>2024-12-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/12/12/The-Post-Scarcity-Vineyard</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/12/The-Post-Scarcity-Vineyard/"><![CDATA[<img src="{{ '/assets/images/meditation.png' | relative_url }}" alt="Game Art" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 600px; height: auto;">

I think we are on the cusp of a meaning crisis. Many, possibly most, derive their meaning from the work they do. If they are in a specialized profession, they have invested a great deal of time, energy, and money to arrive at where they are. They’ve gone to university, perhaps they’ve received an advanced degree, they’ve given many years of effort, sacrificed many nights away from their family, but by God have they done it!

I like the ‘rosebud’ thought experiment. In *Citizen Kane* (1941), Kane utters his final deathbed word, ‘rosebud’, which, as it transpires in the movie, is the name of his childhood sled. For this wealthy and powerful newspaper magnate, rosebud represents a joyful before time, a lost innocence, a longing for a bygone time when he was not consumed by his ongoing pursuit for wealth and power.

In the year 2000, the game *The Sims* was released. *The Sims* is a life-simulation PC game where players create a virtual person (a sim) and manage their relationships, careers, homes, and daily lives. I was going on twelve when *The Sims* was released—it was a formative game of my childhood.

In *The Sims*, there was a cheat code you could activate by pressing `Ctrl + Shift + C`, which brought up a command bar. In homage to *Citizen Kane* (not a reference I would have understood at the time), you could type the word `rosebud`, and it would give you $1000 (or 1000 simoleons, the in-game currency). You could do this as many times as you wanted. In other words, it was an unlimited money cheat code.

The thought experiment, therefore, is quite simple: if you had unlimited money, what would you do? What would you do today? Where would you see yourself years from now? How would you live your life?

With few exceptions, I don’t think many would continue in their 9-to-5 jobs. Initially, people might satisfy their material desires—buying cars, homes, and dining in fancy restaurants. But beyond that, we could imagine a sort of meaning crisis ensuing: where would they now derive their purpose? 

This question has implications for how we prepare for the future. If you were deciding what to study at university today, I would strongly advise against focusing solely on technical subjects. Instead, consider immersing yourself in the humanities—philosophy, history, literature, or the arts. These fields nurture critical thinking, creativity, and an understanding of what it means to live well, qualities that will be essential in a post-scarcity world. 

Once freed from the demands of work, people might turn their attention to hobbies, prioritizing physical and mental wellness, or delve into subjects like philosophy, history, or spirituality. They may pursue creative expression and, perhaps most importantly, deepen their relationships with community, family, and friends.

In my previous life as a religious minister, I had the privilege of speaking to quite a few people in their dying days. My enduring observation from this time, and from these conversations, is the fact that people on their deathbed do not discuss the meaningful work they have done in their life—it never happens. The bereaved often put a strong emphasis upon what an individual did for a living, but the dying almost exclusively talk about their meaningful relationships, family, and friends.

I am therefore tempted to conclude, from rosebud and from deathbed talk, that the supposed meaning that people derive from work is more illusory than they can imagine. It is more of a distraction than anything else. Given the freedom, the money, the opportunity, meaning is still derived from the same place. If they are wise, they will invest more in these areas.

Many people fall into the trap of believing that because they’ve invested significant time, money, and energy into their careers, these should inherently provide them with meaning, purpose, and happiness. This sense of entitlement—though perhaps that’s not quite the right word—stems from the sunk cost fallacy: the idea that past sacrifices justify continued belief in a system that may no longer serve them. Yet meaning, as life and death remind us, is not earned through effort alone. It arises from what we cultivate beyond work—relationships, passions, and the deeper connections that give life its richness.

It reminds me of the Workers in the Vineyard parable that Jesus tells. Some do a whole day of labor, and some do only a few hours, and yet all are paid ‘a denarius’ (Matthew 20:13-15). Jesus is obviously telling this parable to talk about heaven. Some labor for the Lord for a lifetime, whereas others only for a few years, and yet all are given eternal heavenly bliss. How is that fair? Jesus is pressing us to not think in terms of what is fair, and what is just, but rather to delight in the reward—to not think, in other words, about what is due to us.

If it’s not clear already, I’m obviously talking about the post-scarcity world that is going to be delivered to us by artificial intelligence. It remains debatable how far off that is, and perhaps there are periods of strife before we even get there, but it is coming—maybe a few years away, maybe a decade. But what then? What are you going to do once you’re given the cheat code?

In a post-scarcity world, purpose will no longer be tied to merit or effort. The comparisons that once defined us—who worked harder, who sacrificed more—will lose their meaning. The old metrics of success, built around productivity and material gain, will fall away. What remains is the art of living itself.

Living well will become our greatest challenge and our most profound opportunity. It will mean finding joy in the everyday, cultivating relationships, pursuing passions, and engaging with the world not because we must, but because we can. It will require us to redefine success, not as accumulation or achievement, but as the quality of our experiences and the depth of our connections.

This new reality demands wisdom, grace, and creativity. It invites us to focus on what truly matters: the bonds we form, the beauty we create, and the meaning we weave into our days. The art of living well is not about doing more or achieving more—it is about being fully present, embracing life’s possibilities, and choosing, time and again, to live with intention and purpose.]]></content><author><name>Lewis Connolly</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The 10,000-Person Puzzle</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/11/the-10,000-person-puzzle/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 10,000-Person Puzzle" /><published>2024-12-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-12-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/12/11/the-10,000-person-puzzle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/12/11/the-10,000-person-puzzle/"><![CDATA[<img src="{{ '/assets/images/gameart.png' | relative_url }}" alt="Game Art" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 600px; height: auto;">

*Silo* (2023) is a great series; it is set in a seemingly post-apocalyptic world in which 10,000 people live in a ‘silo’ or underground vault. The silo is entirely self-sustaining, across its 144 floors everything is covered, from food to electricity production, to maintenance, medical care, and security, to anything else you can think of, anything which would be necessary to keep the population self-sustained. Through carefully monitoring and sanctioning of childbearing this 10,000-population number is kept static.

This got me thinking about how difficult it would be to maintain a stable population within a closed system. As we can see from population statistics, childbearing from one generation to the next is not at all stable. In the United States, women are having on average 1.62 children; this number has halved since the early 1960s. The replacement rate is 2.1; that is the number to replace the father and the mother, with the .1 accounting for child mortality, women who cannot reproduce, or women who die before they do so. As such, if a woman has fewer than 2.1 children, they are contributing to population decline.

If we assume life expectancy is 77 (I’m not sure if in an underground vault in which everyone’s needs are accommodated for, we should assume a lower or higher life expectancy than the current national average). I’m also assuming no individual autonomy; this would all have to be managed planned-economy style. I’m also assuming that all childbearing is done by women aged 20 to 30—if you’re going to manage this directly, it’s probably best to target the optimal fertility window.

So, the calculation would be 10,000 / 2 = 5000 women. 5000 women / 77 ≈ 65 women per age group. 65 * the 10 optimal fertility years = 650 women at any given time aimiing to have their approximate 2.1 children within their fertility window. In such a limited system, maintaining a stable population is not as simple as meeting replacement rates, however. Genetic variability must also be carefully managed to avoid inbreeding and ensure long-term viability. Additionally, a static system of this size would be highly susceptible to the effects of sudden mortality events, such as disease or disasters. These risks make it imperative to regularly monitor and modulate the population at a granular level.

This would be a good idea for a computer game. Many games are based on exploration, base building, and resource exploitation, but what about a game in which all of that is already done, and the objective is just to maintain the population, optimize for genetic traits, educate and deploy individuals to work within a closed system of this kind.

<img src="{{ '/assets/images/asterism2.png' | relative_url }}" alt="Asterism" style="display: block; margin: 20px auto; max-width: 85px; height: auto;">
<div style="margin-bottom: 20px;"></div>

### Game Design Document

**Vaultborne: A Matchmaker’s Dilemma**  
In *Vaultborne*, you take on the role of population manager for an isolated colony of 10,000 individuals living in a self-contained underground vault. Built to preserve humanity after a global catastrophe, the vault is a sealed, self-sustaining ecosystem where every resource and individual must be carefully managed to ensure survival.

Through strategic matchmaking, education programs, and job allocation, you must maintain genetic diversity, balance labor needs, and preserve the vault's long-term viability. The simulation evolves dynamically, presenting challenges like resource scarcity, genetic drift, and cultural conflicts, ensuring every decision has far-reaching consequences.

---

### Core Gameplay

1. **Matchmaking**
    - Pair individuals for reproduction to optimize genetic diversity and enhance desirable traits.
    - Manage risks like inbreeding and genetic stagnation while responding to mutations or disease outbreaks.
    - Balance societal preferences, such as prioritizing strength, creativity, or discipline, based on the vault’s needs.

2. **Education**
    - Design and manage educational programs to train individuals for critical roles, such as engineers, doctors, and farmers.
    - Choose between broad-based education (generalists) or specialized training (experts) to address immediate and future needs.
    - Shape cultural values, emphasizing traits like innovation or obedience.

3. **Labor Management**
    - Assign individuals to jobs across sectors like agriculture, energy, medicine, security, and governance.
    - Reassign workers during crises, balancing efficiency with morale and long-term consequences.

4. **Morale and Culture**
    - Make decisions that influence cultural trends, like valuing collectivism over individualism or creativity over discipline.
    - Maintain morale through fair policies, festivals, and cultural initiatives—or risk rebellion and productivity loss.

---

### Setting and Themes

**Setting:**  
A sealed underground vault designed for long-term human survival. Limited resources, environmental maintenance, and psychological challenges define the colony's existence.

**Themes:**  
- **Survival:** Navigate the balance between short-term needs and generational stability.  
- **Ethics:** Make tough decisions about individuals vs. the collective good.  
- **Legacy:** Shape the genetic and cultural future of humanity.  

---

### Dynamic Events

- **Genetic Crises:** Disease outbreaks or harmful mutations threaten the vault’s survival.  
- **Resource Failures:** Systems break down, requiring creative problem-solving.  
- **Cultural Conflicts:** Competing ideologies within the vault create social unrest.  
- **Ethical Dilemmas:** Choose between sacrificing individuals or jeopardizing the population.

---

### Key Features

- **Dynamic Population Simulation:** Every individual has unique genetic and cultural traits. Generational growth is directly affected by your matchmaking and educational decisions.  
- **Indirect Control:** Use policy sliders and targeted actions to influence the vault without direct micromanagement.  
- **Long-Term Strategy:** Plan for generations while addressing immediate crises.  
- **Emergent Narratives:** Follow influential families or key individuals as their traits and ideologies shape the vault.

---

### Art and Sound Direction

**Visual Style:**  
- A clean, data-driven interface complemented by isometric views of the vault.  
- Detailed family trees and individual portraits highlight generational evolution.

**Sound:**  
- Ambient soundscapes (e.g., machinery, distant chatter) create an immersive environment.  
- Adaptive music shifts with the vault’s morale or major events.

---

### Target Audience

- Fans of management sims like *Oxygen Not Included*, *Frostpunk*, or *Surviving Mars*.  
- Players who enjoy generational strategy games like *Crusader Kings*.  
- Gamers drawn to ethical dilemmas and long-term planning.]]></content><author><name>Lewis Connolly</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sunk Cost, the Meaning Crisis, &amp;amp; Taste</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/15/sunk-cost-the-meaning-crisis-and-taste/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sunk Cost, the Meaning Crisis, &amp;amp; Taste" /><published>2024-11-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-11-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/15/sunk-cost-the-meaning-crisis-and-taste</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/15/sunk-cost-the-meaning-crisis-and-taste/"><![CDATA[Last night, I listened to an interview with Gwern Branwen. Since he is an anonymous online writer, his identity was concealed using a computer-generated avatar and an AI-generated voice. He got me thinking, as I’m inclined to do, so I’m going to let my thoughts wander and see what appears on the page. Branwen’s writings cover a broad range of topics, but his main focus is artificial intelligence—specifically that these models are scaling in a predictable fashion, and as such, superintelligent AI, or AGI, is just around the corner—three years away, or by 2030 at the latest. In the interview, he more or less takes this as a given and considers the implications of what living in such a world might look like and, more pertinently, what this future might mean for how we live our lives now. I am also going to take his timeframe as a given.

Before I reflect on the content of the interview, I want to say a little about what has been called the “meaning crisis.” I think learning a new skill has, in some respects, been rendered useless. I am dyslexic, which has its positives and negatives; dyslexic people have an alternative information processing style, but it obviously makes language a challenge. I can’t say that learning a second language would be impossible, but I can say it’s definitely not going to happen. Even for a neurotypical individual, learning a second language is a challenge. Nevertheless, people do it for many reasons: to communicate with others who speak that language, to immerse themselves in different cultures, to advance their careers, to read literature, or even for love. They commit to the sunk cost in order to reap the rewards. But what if there were a shortcut that got you most of the way there—a device in the ear, for example, that perfectly and seamlessly translated every word in real time into your mother tongue and vice versa? Would the sunk cost still be worth it? If you’d already put in the effort, I doubt you would regret it, but if one were considering learning a language now, on this side of the equation with the device in hand, what then? 

I think there is still a case to be made; there is surely a degree of cognitive flexibility, greater abstract reasoning, and a kind of subjective breadth that comes with learning a second language, but the rewards are surely greatly diminished. The assumption is that AGI in the next few years will make such a device possible. Honestly, we’re pretty close as it is. My guess, then, is that if this technology became ubiquitous, far fewer people would sink the cost.

I’m really just using language learning here as a concrete example to explain something far more wide-reaching. The arrival of AGI will apply across the board. There will be a surplus of intelligence; any task that is cognitively demanding will be possible to outsource to a computer. Now, of course, that does not necessarily mean that all cognitive efforts will be outsourced; we will have a choice. We can do what is pleasurable to us and outsource what is not, such as navigating the intricacies of the healthcare insurance landscape.

So, the point is that when it comes to sunk costs over the next few years, all this impending change greatly alters the equation before us. Let’s take another example: say you wanted to learn how to use some architectural design software. There are many reasons why you might want to do this, but chief among them is probably the economic value that having such a skill may afford you. Perhaps it would eventually lead to freelance architectural plans or maybe even a job with an architectural firm. Even dabbling with architectural design software might open new opportunities. The mere possibility generates a lot of meaning. But now, it’s not possible.

It’s not possible because there will be a surplus of intelligence. The economic value of any heavy-lifting cognitive effort will be rendered negligible. This changes the equation dramatically. It changes much of what has been conventionally thought of as meaningful and renders it meaningless. What are you good at? Meaningless. What is your job? Meaningless. In a culture where the first question people ask is, “What do you do?” we are fast approaching a meaning crisis.

I believe there is meaning to be found, but it requires viewing things very differently. We have to look past many of the cultural and social norms of our age. I think games—specifically computer games—are a useful tool for exploring at least one aspect of meaning. In a game, you generally have an objective. Within the context of the game, what is your meaning, your purpose? It is to work towards that objective. Beyond the game, in the real world, the game is meaningless, but in the game, the game is everything. A game, by definition, creates artificial limitations—parameters that, if you abide by them, give meaning. Imagine if life were like this: a series of games, a series of objectives.

Now to say something about the Branwen interview. One of his underlying assumptions is the extent to which it is wrong to think of AGI as human-like intelligence; it is often erroneously described this way. Just because artificial intelligence can perform heavy-lifting cognitive efforts as well as, or better than, the best human, does not mean it intellectually experiences reality as we do. Human intelligence and computer intelligence are very different. In particular, humans experience reality subjectively in a way that computers cannot (in this interview, he does not get into whether this may change). As such, there is something of value we can do now that AGI cannot replicate better, faster, or cheaper: express a preference.

I hadn’t considered this before, but I think there is something quite profound in this observation. Preferences, desires, evaluations, judgments—all the stuff of subjectivity—cannot be made wrong. It may even be a kind of commodity that becomes valuable in this age to come. I’m talking about taste. What should we be doing over the next few years? We should be writing down what we like, and the challenging part, I think, is really trying to express *why* we like it. Interrogating the why.

It reminds me of *High Fidelity*, the Cusack romantic-comedy from 2000. I’m pretty sure there’s a line in that movie about how “it’s what you like, not what you are like, that matters.” On one level, that comes off as shallow and trite, but perhaps he was hitting on something deeper: maybe it *is* what we like that will define meaning in the years ahead. Right, I’m off to rewatch that movie and figure out why it’s so good.]]></content><author><name>Lewis Connolly</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last night, I listened to an interview with Gwern Branwen. Since he is an anonymous online writer, his identity was concealed using a computer-generated avatar and an AI-generated voice. He got me thinking, as I’m inclined to do, so I’m going to let my thoughts wander and see what appears on the page. Branwen’s writings cover a broad range of topics, but his main focus is artificial intelligence—specifically that these models are scaling in a predictable fashion, and as such, superintelligent AI, or AGI, is just around the corner—three years away, or by 2030 at the latest. In the interview, he more or less takes this as a given and considers the implications of what living in such a world might look like and, more pertinently, what this future might mean for how we live our lives now. I am also going to take his timeframe as a given.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fascism &amp;amp; Pushing the Fat Man</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/05/fascism-and-pushing-the-fat-man/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fascism &amp;amp; Pushing the Fat Man" /><published>2024-11-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-11-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/05/fascism-and-pushing-the-fat-man</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/05/fascism-and-pushing-the-fat-man/"><![CDATA[Most people know the classic trolley problem: a train is hurtling toward five people on the track. You have the option to pull a lever, diverting the train onto another track where there is one bystander. Do you pull the lever, sacrificing the one to save the five? From a utilitarian perspective—where the focus is on maximizing the greatest good or happiness—the answer is yes. One life lost is deemed preferable to five.

To make the hypothetical more visceral, you can make the action you take more direct, more personal, instead of the dispassionate pulling of a lever. One can imagine a fat man standing on a bridge over the track. In the same way, the train is hurtling towards five people, but if you push the fat man over the side of the bridge, it will cause the train to derail, and this will give you the same result: one will die, and five will live. It’s exactly the same outcome; the only difference is you’re not so much an anonymous bystander but you’re in the fray. In theory though, if your answer was yes before, it should be yes now.

Another alternative is instead of talking about trains and tracks, you can talk about sacrificing an innocent individual and harvesting their organs in order to perform life-saving surgery on five people who need those organs in order to live. Again, the outcome is exactly the same – one dies to save the five.

The alternative position is the virtue ethics position, which is the moral argument position: killing an innocent person is inherently wrong and therefore one should not pull the lever or push the fat man even if the outcome is preferable because killing someone, especially killing someone who is innocent, is fundamentally wrong.

Personally, I lean uneasily in this virtue ethics direction. In practice though, I’m really not so sure; I’m torn in both directions. Perhaps if the stakes were more extreme, I would swallow my sense of moral correctness and just pick the utilitarian option—what if it were one innocent person to save ten, or a hundred, or a thousand?

The classic killing-baby-Hitler thought experiment is very similar. You step through a time machine and you’re taken to Austria; you find yourself in a small town in the year 1890, and there in a crib is the little one-year baby Adolf, all cute and innocent looking. Should you kill him? Now by definition in this moment he (not taking into consideration original sin) is completely innocent, but the thought experiment assumes that history will unfold in exactly the same way without intervention, just as the previous thought experiments do not allow for the possibility of those people on the tracks at the last minute jumping out of the way, or the organ-less individuals somehow receiving what they need from somewhere else or alternative care.

No. If you do not kill little baby Adolf, history will unfold exactly how it did, including the Holocaust and the military and civilian casualties of WW2. Conservatively we’re talking about at least 80 million deaths. Now maybe it makes me crazy, but given this equation, I cannot see how you could possibly justify not committing baby murder.

That brings us to the exciting world of the 2024 political election cycle (hope you detected some British irony there). So, the charge goes that Trump is a fascist or that Trump is a Hitler. To quote JD Vance, his running mate, he said in 2016: “I go back and forth between thinking Trump is a cynical asshole like Nixon who wouldn’t be that bad (and might even prove useful) or that he’s America’s Hitler.” Now in reality what people mean by this is very unclear. Does anyone literally think he is going to cause the kind of human suffering that Adolf Hitler caused? I find it highly improbable. Maybe there are some out there that think this; there are idiots out there.

To be clear: If you don’t know me, I am 100% supporting Harris in the election, despite being unable to vote, not being an American citizen. I personally believe that Harris is the strongest candidate on literally every substantive issue. Now, if you were to ask me if I think that I personally, or my family personally, would be better off under Trump or Harris, I am very unsure about that. Perhaps we would be better off under Trump. But I believe that one should vote for who would be better for America at large, not yourself.

I think it is important to highlight this because I, as a middle-class person, and especially, one might make the case, as a white male middle-class individual, am greatly insulated from the negative effects of a possible Trump presidency. I would probably even fare well in the most dystopian, fascistic, Hitlerian America one might imagine—maybe.

So, there is something about this insulatedness of middle-class America that is motivating me to write this. There is a lot of talk amongst liberal Americans about how fascistic and Hitlerian Trump is; I’m torn as to how true this may be. I think Jan 6 was insane, but there are always the checks and balances… But if you think it is true, then there is by definition an existential threat in this country, and as such, at the very least, entertaining a more extreme stance does not seem to me to be out of place—that is unless you don’t *really* think there is a fascistic or Hitlerian threat, or if you take a principled pacifist position. A lot of politics is just theatre after all.

I suspect what is really at play, more than most would like to admit, is this insular middle-class existence factor. For most white middle-class “Americans,” a second Trump presidency won’t change all that much. There will just need to be a bit more theatre, we’ll wear our complaints on our sleeves, but really, why make the fuss?]]></content><author><name>Lewis Connolly</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Most people know the classic trolley problem: a train is hurtling toward five people on the track. You have the option to pull a lever, diverting the train onto another track where there is one bystander. Do you pull the lever, sacrificing the one to save the five? From a utilitarian perspective—where the focus is on maximizing the greatest good or happiness—the answer is yes. One life lost is deemed preferable to five.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Arguing the Bible</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/29/arguing-the-bible/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arguing the Bible" /><published>2024-05-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-05-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/05/29/arguing-the-bible</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/29/arguing-the-bible/"><![CDATA[This is not going to be particularly deep. I was prompted to write something in response to a popular YouTuber. It doesn’t really matter who this individual is, as the observations made were not unique, just everyday atheistic observations. I come at this as someone who self-identifies as a Christian but could just as easily be described as an atheist. I realize this might sound odd, and hopefully, what I write here will clear up some confusion. If not, just buy me a beer, and I’ll happily pontificate further.

The YouTuber in question was getting hung up on the historicity of the Bible. Questions like, *“Did X really happen?”*, *“Did Jesus really walk out of the tomb?”*, *“Was there really an exodus of Jews from Egypt?”* His sparring partner in the conversation was equivocating hard. I can understand why. Given such questions, the desire to equivocate might arise, and I can see why someone might feel frustrated, not believing their questions were being adequately addressed. *“Yes, I get all that, but if I were to get into a time machine and go back to whenever…”* bla bla.

The communication breakdown here has to do with purpose. What was the purpose of the biblical text when it says X or Y? We’re taught in seminary that the Bible is not so much a book, but rather a library, and within this library are different genres, some more historical in nature, and some more poetical. Obviously, this is a gross simplification. However, I don’t believe there are any books in the Bible that rise to the standards of historicity that we could find upon the shelves of our local library’s history section. Rather, I would maintain that historical truth is something that occasionally, but rarely, leaks into the Bible. In other words, recording *‘historical truth’* in the very contemporary sense in which we understand that was not the purpose that inspired the biblical texts.

Rather, the biblical texts are on a mission to persuade their readers of something. And by ‘their readers,’ I’m not talking about us. The individuals who wrote the various books of the Bible obviously could not have entertained the possibility that one day, over 2000 years in the future, individuals would be drinking black energy juice while reading their words in translation off of magic light screens kept in their pockets.

These writers were attempting to persuade their audience of some political or spiritual reality. If anything, it is this that is of utmost importance. Given this, I think the whole *‘Did X really happen?’* framing is basically rendered meaningless. Whether X did or did not happen is not at all what the text is about. I’m torn as to whether it is sometimes worth putting people out of their misery and proclaiming the fact of things one way or another, just so they would cease to entertain such meaningless questions and begin entertaining the text’s purpose.

There is a presumption baked into my reasoning here, and that presumption is that the purposes that the various texts are driving at are worthy of our attention.]]></content><author><name>Lewis Connolly</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is not going to be particularly deep. I was prompted to write something in response to a popular YouTuber. It doesn’t really matter who this individual is, as the observations made were not unique, just everyday atheistic observations. I come at this as someone who self-identifies as a Christian but could just as easily be described as an atheist. I realize this might sound odd, and hopefully, what I write here will clear up some confusion. If not, just buy me a beer, and I’ll happily pontificate further.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Simply Listening</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/25/simply-listening/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Simply Listening" /><published>2024-05-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-05-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/05/25/simply-listening</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/25/simply-listening/"><![CDATA[I recall my last sitting. I awoke the other night; my wife and daughter were fast asleep. Let me describe the experience to you. This exercise was motivated by a desire to approach this—whatever word we’re using to describe it—with more intentionality. This intentionality colors what follows.

I chose to sit in the backroom of our house; it’s a multifunctional room, primarily the dining room, secondarily my wife’s office. I believed it was the quietest room in the house. I don’t think that anymore. When you’re really listening, just sitting for a moment, the fact that your house is in North Carolina becomes abundantly evident. You hear the cicadas, which ordinarily disappear into the background. They are undeniably present.

I was sitting on my Amazon-purchased meditation pillow on a rainy and windy night. Those were the second and third most prevalent sounds: the rain on the roof and the wind blowing through the conifers, occasionally causing the house to creak. In this backroom sits our secondary freezer, which clicks on every 10 to 15 minutes. What is usually a quiet, almost imperceptible sound, generally dissolves into the background. In this moment, it roared through the room, accompanied by a high-pitched electronic whine. I attempted to accept this irritating noise, ultimately unsuccessfully.

When I managed to look past these “external” sounds, my thoughts came to mind. And so I listened. When I write of listening, I mean it in the broadest sense—not just audible sensations, but everything. We often distinguish between exterior sensations from our senses and our interior world of thoughts and raw experience. However, in the way it comes to us, I don’t think such a distinction can be made. There is nothing other than our unified field of experience, and it is to this that we listen.

Thoughts came across the field of my experience: the rain, the wind, and a deeper sense of frustration. I came to this backroom specifically because I desired to get something out of this experience. There was an underlying frustration because I had not yet arrived, had not yet sucked the marrow out of existence, had not yet lived. There was an obvious, aching lack, an instinctive reaction for a resolution, and then there was just this—a yawning nothing that always responds.

I’m sitting in my backroom. My thoughts concern my predilections, cultural matters, politics, but then more substantively, that I should remove the second freezer from this room, that I should rearrange the room entirely. I should experiment with different room layouts to maximize the space’s potential for my spiritual practice. There’s an absurdity to this, an incessant draw pulling my focus away from where it ought to be. Where it ought? What ought?

I need to “listen.” I need to listen in a way that does not pre-judge—a listening devoid of an ought. A listening without objective, preference, or need—a simple listening. So often, I am arrested by the sense that I need to meditate to become spiritually advanced, the Jedi master I aspire to become. Again, obviously an absurd notion. Absurd, but I don’t think I’m alone in this. I think it is difficult for our egos to give ourselves over to almost anything without entertaining the notion that we may become proficient in it, maybe even an authority on the matter. They will surely circle the block in search of our oh-so-great wisdom.

I’m sitting in the backroom. Let’s not call it meditation. The trouble with that word is that everyone thinks it requires doing something, like emptying the mind or reciting some mantra. I prefer the term sitting, not so open to misinterpretation. There is no technique, nothing to know. All there is, is sitting and listening.

Thoughts arise, and after a moment of wandering, my thoughts return to the realization that I’m currently sitting here. That’s not something you have to do; your thoughts wander back to your present reality without forethought. Some thoughts plague us with greater persistence, perhaps irritating or even enraging. Even the most mundane nothing of thoughts can induce a sort of rage, clouding the way after whatever we ought to be after. You can’t run from these thoughts; you probably can’t even breathe or mantra your way out of them. It’s far better to just listen. Listen not so much to the intellectualization of the rage-inducing thoughts, but instead bring awareness to what you are feeling—the breathlessness, the tightness, the ache behind your eyes. One need not seek to move away from such intrusive thoughts. And yet, when we focus on the emotive quality of such thoughts, they do seem to dissolve. This is to say that when we focus on the emotive content rather than our intellectualization of said things, they dissolve. Not focusing on the why or the preceding history of x or y, but just the experience as it shows up now.

I’m in my backroom. I’m aware of the environment around me—the rain, the wind, the hum. I’m aware of my thoughts, the narrative into which everything is woven: who is sitting here, Lewis is. He is having these experiences; every thought correlates with who I know Lewis to be. Lewis knows himself to be living in North Carolina, so of course, he experiences the weather, the bugs, the condition befitting a man currently sitting on a cushion in his backroom in the old north state. My thoughts likewise correlate with who I believe myself to be. I am someone interested in politics, philosophy, spirituality, film, history, interior design, and so forth. As such, when my thoughts spill into such areas, they do not take me by surprise.

Listening requires no such orientation of my thoughts. A thought may occur. Let’s use a real example: I’m sitting in my backroom, and I start thinking of Jennifer Leigh’s missing teeth in Tarantino’s *The Hateful Eight*. I wonder how this effect was achieved. I assume Quentin Tarantino didn’t use CGI to pull off such an effect; that would go against his filmmaking ethos.

I’m supposed to be meditating, or rather, sitting. I shouldn’t be thinking about how certain film effects are pulled off. And so I feel frustrated with myself. I’ll refocus, breathe deeper, give more attention to my breath. I think, however, you can even see the roots of her teeth in those close-up shots, the ones where she’s covered in blood, scenes not unlike some from *Kill Bill*.

In a moment, my thoughts return to the room—the rain, the freezer’s hum. Focusing in on the hum, there’s a nagging sensation, a pointed pain that manifests in my head. I focus on that pointed pain, with its edges that lie towards the front of my skull. My attention draws something from the experience; it blurs the edges. Is my head even aching? I’d probably say yes, but with focus, with attention, it no longer resides front of mind. There is a quieting that occurs, not a quieting willed, rather a quieting that occurs naturally. It is not sought, simply arrived at by way of listening. I shouldn’t even state that it has resulted by way of my sitting practice, per se. I don’t think one should be pursuing it as some end to be striven for. Do not strive. Simply listen.

Don’t set goals or seek self-improvement; these only act to take you away from the current moment. Part of what it is to listen is to experience your thoughts as they come, to be aware of the manner in which they arise, what thoughts beget others, what emotions. The emotions will come: bemusement, frustration, anger. Our purpose here is not to resist such emotions but rather to note them, and not so much in a rationalistic way. Note these emotions in terms of their full felt experience, their physicality, their spatial quality. There is the I who perceives, the I that listens.]]></content><author><name>Lewis Connolly</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I recall my last sitting. I awoke the other night; my wife and daughter were fast asleep. Let me describe the experience to you. This exercise was motivated by a desire to approach this—whatever word we’re using to describe it—with more intentionality. This intentionality colors what follows.]]></summary></entry></feed>